Well, all right y'all. It's time to talk
about the progressives. That sassy group
of early 20th century reformers that
wanted to get the government all up in
everyone's crap and gird thyself because
this is a beefy one. So, if you're ready
to get them brain cows milked, let's get
to it. Okay, so first let me tell you
who the progressives were and why when
it came to gressing, they were pretty
much pros. So, the progressive movement
sought to reform the social, political,
and economic abuses that had occurred as
a result of late 19th century
industrialization by means of
significant government intervention.
Like I remember from the last unit that
during the guilded age the general
attitude among the elite was that
government intervention was the root of
all social and economic problems. But
the progressives believe that government
intervention was the solution to all
social and economic ills. Or to put it
in terms we used in unit 6. Back then
everybody wanted big daddy government to
get his hands off. But the progressives
wanted to get those meaty government
hands right back on the economy and
society and politics and dang near all
the rest of it. Or to put it yet another
way, the guilded age attitude was
seeking freedom from government, while
the progressive era was more like
seeking freedom through government. Oh,
and by the way, if you want note guys to
follow along with this video and all my
videos, check that link in the
description. Okay, now you also need to
know that the progressives were kind of
like heirs to the populist movement from
the 1890s because remember the populists
had all kinds of reforms that they tried
to enact, but bless their agrarian
hearts, many of those reforms were
unsuccessful. But progressives took up
many of those populist reforms and
actually got them implemented. And I'll
tell you more about them in a moment. So
you might say that the progressives were
just the populists and a sexier fun. But
I need to be clear that although there
were similarities between the two
movements, there were significant
differences too. For example, populists
were largely concerned about reform for
rural Americans while progressives
concerned themselves with urban reformed
and industrialized cities. Additionally,
populists mostly represented the lower
working class, while progressives tended
to come from the middle and upper
classes. And while everything I said is
a pretty decent definition of the
progressive movement as a whole, you
also need to know that the progressives
were made up of many diverse groups. And
so while they shared a basic agreement
on the methods for change, they often
disagreed on what needed changing. So
among the progressives, you had
Protestant church leaders, feminists,
labor union leaders, African-Americans,
and many more, each of which called for
different kinds of reforms. And so now,
let me parade before your thirsty brain
a handful of those diverse goals for
which the progressives worked in the
first couple decades of the 20th
century. And hold on to your butts
because there are no less than six of
these goals that you're going to need to
know. So the first target of progressive
reform was racial segregation. And
within this camp, progressives basically
held three different attitudes toward
the problem. So, some progressives
supported racial segregation in the
South, while others ignored its
presence, while still others worked to
dismantle it. The latter being almost
exclusively black progressives. For
example, Booker T. Washington was a
black reformer who essentially ignored
segregation. At least, like that's how
his detractors would put it. So,
Washington discouraged black Americans
from actively fighting against
segregation through social or political
movements. Instead, he encouraged black
Americans to get educated and work on
developing American virtues like thrift
and abstinence, which would eventually
result in more social and political
power. And to that end, he founded the
All Black Tuskegee Institute in Alabama,
which focused its curriculum on teaching
students virtuous habits and practical
skills for industrial jobs. So, in some,
Washington believed that if black
Americans became educated and
economically vital to American industry,
then segregation would gradually
disappear since white Americans couldn't
afford to continue marginalizing their
black neighbors. But then on the very
other side of the debate was the fiery
Ida B. Wells who rejected Washington's
practicalism and encouraged black
Americans to resist segregation. Now she
herself was a journalist and used her
talents to speak out viferously against
the lynching of blacks in the south. And
when white supremacists destroyed her
printing equipment, she fled to Chicago
where she continued her work to
dismantle white supremacy in the south.
But then there was web deo who occupied
a kind of middle position between
Washington and wells. He agreed with
Washington that black Americans ought to
seek every means of self-improvement to
which they had access. But he also
believed that the only true path to
equality required equal voting rights
and the complete removal of segregated
public facilities. And so to that end,
do the boys founded the all black
Niagara movement which formerly fought
for black voting rights and equal access
to public facilities for black
Americans. Now over time, the
organization struggled to achieve its
goals. But they eventually joined with
other white reformers like Florence
Kelly and Jane Adams to create the
National Association for the Advancement
of Color People. And the NAACP focused
on challenging segregation and black
lynching in the courts. and on the whole
was way more successful than the Niagara
movement. In fact, many of their
judicial victories laid the groundwork
for the successes of the civil rights
movement that we'll talk about in the
next unit. Okay. Now, a second major
reform for which progressives worked was
the expansion of popular participation
in politics. Now, as a general rule,
progressives trusted common people with
political power rather than elites and
therefore they worked to transfer power
away from the top and toward average
Americans. And to that end, progressives
worked toward four major changes in the
political landscape. First was the use
of the secret ballot, otherwise known by
its sassier name, the Australian ballot.
Anyway, to progressives, a major arena
of political corruption was the public
nature of voting. Like, prior to this,
political parties themselves printed
ballots which listed their own party
members and then would watch as voters
marked their candidates. And if you
can't smell why such a system might lead
to political corruption as it did with
the dominance of urban political
machines, then you need to get your
sniffer check. But the progressives
fixed this problem by introducing the
secret ballot which was adopted first by
Massachusetts in 1888 and then within
two decades all states had adopted this
reform. And then the second way
progressives sought to return political
power to the people was by means of the
direct primary. It was introduced by
Wisconsin governor and winner of the
hair lottery. And that enabled ordinary
citizens to choose their party's
candidate which had the effect of
siphoning power from corrupt political
machines. And then third progressives
worked for the direct election of
senators in Congress which was another
carryover from the populace. Recall from
the last period that it was a pretty
common practice for members of Congress
to receive bribes and incentives from
large corporations in order to keep
those businesses free from government
regulation. And this was possible
because the Constitution mandated that
senators be elected via state
legislatores. And so in order to bring
more power back to average Americans,
progressives pushed for the direct
election of senators and they very much
succeeded. In 1913, the 17th amendment
to the constitution was ratified which
officially put the election of senators
into the hands of the people. And then
the fourth way progressives transfer
political power to the people was by
enabling greater voter participation
through the initiative, the referendum,
and the recall. The initiative was a
mechanism voters could use to require
legislators to vote on a bill that they
may have otherwise ignored. The
referendum allowed Americans to directly
vote on proposed bills instead of
leaving that entirely to their elected
representatives. And then the recall
gave voters the power to remove an
elected politician from office before
they had completed their term. All
right, now let's turn to the third major
reform for which progressives worked.
And that would be an increase in
government efficiency by applying the
principles of tailorism. So recall from
unit 6 that I introduced you to
Frederick Taylor who introduced the idea
of scientific management which aimed to
make factory work more efficient and
therefore more productive and
profitable. Now since the massive
changes that accompanied
industrialization occurred so rapidly,
national and local governments struggled
to keep up with and adapt to the
changing environment. And that's the
reason that political machines dominated
local elections. Namely because they
organized themselves to offer services
that the government did not. However,
progressives believe that such
corruption and inefficiency could be
remedied by applying the principles of
scientific management to the government.
So to that end, many cities adopted the
commission form of government in which a
group of elected commissioners ran
various departments as if they were
businesses. Additionally, some urban
governments created a new position
called the city manager who acted as a
kind of CEO for the city and assured
that its local programs ran with peak
efficiency. And so in this way, local
governments began to see their people
less as constituents and more as
shareholders. Which is to say,
governments were no longer run like
governments, but like businesses. All
right, let's keep on moving and talk
about the fourth major progressive
effort during this period, namely
immigration reform. So immigrants from
Europe and Asia continued to arrive in
huge numbers to the United States during
the first decades of the 20th century.
And this reality inspired different
reactions from different progressives.
For example, some progressives like
Margaret Sanger worked among poor urban
immigrants to reduce the number of
children they had. And to remedy that,
Sanger became a leading advocate of
birth control. But you should also know
that Sanger's efforts were very much
informed by popular eugenics theories of
the day. In other words, she believed
that the quantity and more to the point,
the quality of the white race would be
improved if non-white women had fewer
children. But then other progressives
like Jane Adams worked to establish
settlement houses in urban areas which
offered immigrants various services like
healthcare and education and child care
for working parents. But don't worry
because Adams' work was also rooted in
eugenics. So, you know, there it is. But
then still other progressives,
especially leaders of labor unions,
advocated for legislation to restrict
immigration since, in their estimation,
these foreign workers competed with
Americans for jobs and drove wages down.
And they ultimately achieved a major
victory with the passage of the
Immigration Act of 1917 and then another
in 1921, which cut off virtually all
Asian immigrants and significantly
restricted European immigration. And now
it's time to talk about the fifth major
target of progressive reform, and that's
the conservation and preservation of
America's natural resources. And unless
my eyes deceive me, it seems like your
natural resources for continuing to pay
attention to this exceedingly beefy
video are dang near tapped out. So slap
yourself in the face, take a nap, do
what you got to do, but let's keep
going. Anyway, progressives sought to
apply their beloved principles of
efficiency to the use and protection of
America's natural resources. And this
became especially urgent after the
closing of the frontier in 1890. But
just like every other reform I've
mentioned, this one too sparked a debate
between two opposing sides. The
conservationist and the preservationist.
And I know they sound like the same
thing, but they're not. So let me he
explain it up real nice for you.
Conservationists like Gford Pinshow
believe that America's natural resources
like forests and coal and oil etc should
be extracted and used but with an
attempt to balance that use with
maintaining the beauty of the landscape.
On the other hand, preservationists like
John Mure aimed to protect the natural
beauty of the landscape by preventing
all resource extraction. And as it
turned out, the progressive
environmental movement gained a powerful
advocate in the federal government with
the election of President Theodore
Roosevelt, who issued scores of
executive orders to protect America's
landscape and wildlife. Additionally,
Roosevelt oversaw the creation of three
protected national parks. And I'll tell
you more about him in the next section.
And then finally, the sixth general goal
of progressive reform was to expose
corruption in all areas of government
and society. And the folks most
responsible for this task were a group
of investigative journalists known as
the muckreers. They wrote scathing
essays and articles which exposed
corruption in government and business.
And their work provided no small amount
of energy for wider progressive reform,
especially among their middle-class
readers. And I reckon I need to give you
a proper introduction to a few of them.
First, meet Ida Tarbell, who targeted
John D. Rockefeller's company, Standard
Oil by exposing a myriad of illegal
activities that enabled it to virtually
eliminate all competition from the
market. Second, meet a Chinese American
muckreaker named Ingp Punchu, who wrote
to expose the gross injustices of the
Chinese Exclusion Act and showed in
detail how Chinese Americans suffered
under its terms. And then probably the
most famous muckreaker of all was Upton
Sinclair, whose book, The Jungle, showed
in horrifying detail the unsanitary
practices of industrial meat packing
plants. And so ultimately, by opening
Americans eyes to injustice and
corruption, the muckreers were able to
score some major legislative victories.
For example, after Upton Sinclair's book
was published, Congress passed the Pure
Food and Drug Act, as well as the Meat
Inspection Act, both of which provided
government oversight in the food
industry to ensure that Americans were
eating food that was safe and free of
contamination. And that's another
example of the progressive belief that
no small part of the government's job
was to uphold and protect the welfare of
its citizens. And now, my dear pupil, we
have made it to the last section, and
this one is all about how progressivism
played out on the stage of national
politics. And in order to do that, I
want to briefly introduce you to two
progressive presidents and two
constitutional amendments. All right,
first let's meet Teddy Roosevelt.
Pictured here staring into the eyes of a
grizzly bear and deciding that he could
probably kill it with his bare hands if
he needed to. Now, Roosevelt believed it
was detrimental to the American people
that administrations during the guilded
age had so often sided with big
businesses against the interests of the
working class. Therefore, he aimed to
provide what he called a square deal for
both parties and he soon got an
opportunity to test how square his deal
could be. In 1902, Pennsylvania coal
miners went on strike to demand better
pay and the recognition of their union.
But the owners of the mine and the
railroad companies that shipped its coal
refused to budge even slightly to their
demands. And so Roosevelt flexed his
executive muscles and threatened to send
in federal troops to operate the mines
if an agreement was not reached. And
ultimately the business owners backed
down and offered their workers better
wages and reduced working hours but
without recognizing the legitimacy of
their union. And so in that way
Roosevelt demonstrated that he could
work for the good of both big businesses
and the working class. And then
Roosevelt also applied progressive
principles to the regulation of
businesses, specifically trusts, and
more specifically bad trust that had
illegally eliminated competition in the
market and relied on predatory pricing.
To that end, Roosevelt began rigorously
enforcing the Sherman Antitrust Act of
1890, which had been ignored by previous
administrations. But Roosevelt wielded
this law like a dang infinity stone and
broke up more than 40 trusts, thereby
earning himself the nickname the
trustbuster. And there is so much more
that I could say about Roosevelt, but I
need to introduce you to the second
major progressive president, Woodro
Wilson. And on his first day in office,
Wilson got busy enacting sweeping
economic reform by attacking what he
called the triple wall of privilege,
which included tariffs, banking, and
trust. To that end, in 1913, he led
Congress to pass the Underwood Tariff
Act, which reduced tariffs on
manufactured goods on which many rural
Americans depended. And all of this was
in response to the financial panics that
occurred in the last quarter of the 19th
century. And that means that under these
progressive presidents, the whole LZ
fair era of government intervention was
slowly being amended. Additionally,
under Wilson's leadership, the 16th
amendment was passed and it created a
national income tax. It was a populist
reform that had failed in the 1890s but
found success in the 20th century. And
then Wilson also championed banking
reform. Picking up the complaint from
the populist, Wilson argued that the
gold standard created unnecessary
economic hardship on average Americans.
And to solve that problem, he proposed
the creation of a national banking
system, namely the Federal Reserve. And
the Fed would regulate the money supply
and set interest rates according to the
changing needs of the country and
therefore create the occasion for more
widespread economic flourishing. Okay.
And finally, let me tell you about two
more constitutional amendments passed
during this period that reflect
progressive sensibilities. Now, I
already mentioned the 16th and 17th
amendments earlier, so make sure you
keep those on the list. Okay. So, in
1919, the 18th amendment was ratified,
which made prohibition the law of the
land. Now, don't forget that since the
second half of the 19th century, middle
class women reformers had campaigned and
organized for the elimination of alcohol
consumption since they believed it to be
a chief cause of moral decay and
political corruption and social disorder
among the working class. And thanks to
their efforts, many states had banned
alcohol by 1917. But once the United
States entered World War I in 1917,
prohibition reformers saw their chance
to make a change on the national state.
They argued that the grain that was used
to make alcohol was critical to the war
effort and therefore a national ban on
alcohol was the only logical move. And
apparently the requisite number of
Americans agreed and the prohibition
amendment was added to the constitution
until its repeal in 1933. And then in
1920, the 19th amendment was ratified
which officially at long last recognized
the rights of American women to vote.
Now recall that women have been publicly
organizing for voting rights since the
Senica Falls Convention in 1848. And
while that movement grew significantly
in scope during the Gilded Age, they saw
little successes on the national scale.
However, by the progressive era, the
wider world was changing with respect to
women. You see, democratic countries
throughout the world were recognizing
women's right to vote. And that momentum
provided energy for a renewed activism
for women's suffrage in the United
States, which as I mentioned was
ultimately successful. All right. You
can click here to watch my other videos
for unit 7 or you can click here to grab
my video note guides which are going to
help you get all the contents of this
course firmly crammed into your brain
fold. And give yourself a high five for
getting through this one and I'll catch
you on the flipflop. Himler out.